WHAT WOULD YOU DO
（要是因為自己沒犯下的罪）
IF YOU WERE ARRESTED FOR A CRIME YOU DIDN'T COMMIT?
（而被逮捕，您會怎麼做？）
I would fight until the end because I didn't do anything bad.
當然是奮戰到底了 我又沒做什麼壞事
You didn't do anything? Don't be ridiculous!
什麼都沒做？別開玩笑了
I know you did it!
我很清楚你都做了些什麼
They're called false charges, right?
那就是所謂的冤罪吧
It doesn't really happen nowadays, does it?
現在這時代不太會發生吧？
Don't underestimate the police investigation.
少瞧不起警方的調查了
Only you were at the crime scene!
現場除了你以外沒別人了吧
If I didn't do it, I could stay calm during the questioning.
既然沒做，被偵訊也沒差吧
People who are innocent but say they did it are too weak-minded!
是那些明明沒犯罪 卻承認的人意志太薄弱了
If you still won't admit it, I'll really…
要是你再這樣死不認罪
I did it.
是我做的
I…
是我…
set the house on fire.
放火燒了我家
THERE WAS A YOUNG LAWYER WHO CHALLENGES FALSE VERDICTS
（一位年輕律師 為了冤罪受害者挺身而出）
Oh, Mr. Kurokawa?
黑川律師啊
It is unusual for young lawyers nowadays
以最近的年輕律師來說 算是很少見的了
to have so much passion for criminal cases.
居然對刑事案件那麼有熱情
INDICTMENT
（起訴狀）
"Set his home on fire…"
“在自家縱火…”
Mr. Kurokawa?
黑川律師？
He's a good senior.
他是個很棒的前輩呢
He's easy-going, even towards me, a paralegal--
連對我這個律師助理也很親切…
Hey!
-欸 -哎呀
-Go over there and do some work. -Okay.
-你給我去旁邊專心工作 -是
I'm the head of the office, Beppu.
我是所長別府
Kurokawa is brilliant as the lawyer in charge of criminal cases,
黑川律師在處理刑事案件上 是非常優秀的律師
but our office puts most of our resources into corporate law cases.
但本事務所的專長是企業法務案件
We also deal with difficult mergers and acquisitions cases.
難解的合併案也接受委託處理
For legal consultation, please contact us at Hoshundo Law Office.
有法律困擾的人 請務必聯絡我們保駿堂法律事務所
SET IT ON FIRE, ESCAPED THE HOME
（潑灑煤油縱火）
He confessed his crime.
坦承了犯行啊
Mr. Kurokawa?
黑川律師嗎？
KAEDE WAKURA, LAWYER
（和倉楓，刑事部門律師）
Frankly, his behavior is entirely unacceptable.
老實說，他這人實在太糟糕了
Look at his desk!
看看這張桌子
It's a mess, isn't it?
亂七八糟的，對吧？
He's sloppy by nature.
他根本就是個邋遢的人
The most unbelievable thing is
還有最難以置信的
he is poor, so he lives in our office's storage room.
就是他缺錢到 要住在事務所的雜物間裡
Anyway, why don't you cover me in your show instead?
比起這個，要貼身採訪就採訪我吧
-Ouch! -I am sorry!
-好痛 -真抱歉
-Are you okay? -I'm okay.
-你沒事吧？ -沒事
Calm down, Miss Wakura.
和倉律師，你也冷靜點嘛
I'm sorry!
很抱歉
Hey, please don't get in the way of our filming.
真是的，別打擾採訪啊
I am sorry.
真抱歉
She just joined our office a month ago.
她一個月前才來我們這裡
It's a long story.
之前似乎發生了不少事
Yeah, many things happened, and Miss Wakura is desperate.
沒錯，經歷了很多事 所以她特別焦躁呢
After all, she used to work at James Yuri Law Office
畢竟她原本可是
James Yuri?
詹姆士友利
-The largest law firm in Tokyo? -Here!
-不就是都內最大的律師事務所嗎？ -來
-Why did you come to this law office? -Here you are. Sorry.
-怎麼會淪落這種地方？ -給你，不好意思
It's a long story.
-就說了一言難盡 -聽說因為打上司被開除
If you're telling a story, tell it accurately.
請你說話精準點
I was sexually assaulted and my self-defense resulted
是我對惡質性騷擾採取正當防衛 而對方進行了不當解僱
Sorry to hear that.
那還真是遺憾啊
By the way, where is the center of our attention today?
話說今天最重要的主角在哪？
He shut himself in at home because he doesn't want to be interviewed.
他關在家裡，說不想接受採訪
It isn't his home, it's our storage room.
那裡才不是他家，是雜物間
TAKU KUROKAWA'S HOME
（黑川拓的家）
Yes? Oh. Good afternoon.
來了，辛苦了
-Good afternoon. -What's the matter?
-辛苦了 -等等…幹嘛？
We told you that we would be visiting today, Mr. Taku Kurokawa.
應該已經告知過你 今天有採訪了，黑川律師
I'm sorry,
不好意思，但我不是已經拒絕了嗎？
Your office's head and Mr. Yufuin gave us permission.
已經獲得所長許可 湯布院先生也拜託你了對吧？
Kurokawa, is it really not okay?
黑川，還是不行嗎？
I'm just really not good at this, and I'm afraid that
這…我真的很不擅長接受訪問
people will get the wrong idea if I appear on TV.
也怕上了電視會招惹奇怪的誤會
I am really sorry… Thanks.
抱歉，不好意思…
I think we should come again another day.
看來今天還是算了吧
I'm sorry.
真抱歉，還勞煩你們特地跑一趟
Let's go.
收隊
The guy seems laid back.
那個人感覺很散漫啊
Is the lawyer so brilliant that he's worth covering, Miss Arima?
他真的是值得 有馬前輩你窮追不捨的律師嗎？
Taku Kurokawa, 29 years old. He's in the third year of his law career.
黑川拓，29歲，擔任律師第三年
He has won and overturned five false charges so far.
至今已經成功逆轉 五起刑事案件，無罪獲勝
Five in three years?
三年才打贏五件？
Do you know how hard it is to overturn a false charge
你知道在日本司法制度底下 要逆轉成無罪有多難嗎？
No.
不知道
If a person is prosecuted, they are almost 100% guilty.
只要被起訴了 幾乎百分之百會判有罪
-Then-- -Yes.
-所以說… -沒錯
Five cases in three years is an amazing number.
三年就能打贏五件 可是非常驚人的數字
But is he so good that a TV show would interview him?
但有誇張到電視台要特地來拍嗎？
All five cases were theft or minor bodily injury.
五件都是些竊盜或輕度傷害 也不是多難的案子吧
Miss Arima has always been interested in false convictions.
有馬小姐從以前就特別關注冤案
I've known her for a long time too.
和我已經是老交情了
Even theft and assault charges are difficult to win in court.
就算是竊盜或傷害 要打贏官司也很難的
Well, he's worth interviewing more than someone
比起某位毫無實績的律師 更值得訪問吧
I've only been given chores since I joined your office!
那是因為到了這裡後 除了打雜外什麼都沒讓我做
Mr. Kurokawa, I've asked you many times,
黑川律師，拜託你好多次了 差不多也該清理桌子了吧
Sure, I'll do it later.
好，待會我一定會清
What are you looking for?
你在找什麼？
Documents of an arson case. The client will be here soon.
火災的資料，委託人馬上就到了
What? Client?
咦？委託人？
Did you take a case?
有人委託辯護嗎？
Yes, some days ago.
對，是幾天前委託的
Didn't I tell you?
怪了，我沒說嗎？
You didn't tell us! Why do you never do things properly?
根本沒聽說啊 為什麼這種事都不好好告知啊？
Sorry, I was too forgetful.
真抱歉，我一時忘記了
Found it.
找到了
Gosh!
真是的
I am sorry.
抱歉
LAWYERS CONFRONTING FALSE CHARGES CAN THEY SOLVE THE ARSON?
（面對冤案的律師們）
Stop talking shit!
別開玩笑了
What do you know about me? Take it back!
你到底懂什麼？給我收回那句話
Why would I have set the fire?
我怎麼可能在那裡縱火？
I will use all my power to investigate and fight for you.
我會徹底調查，奮戰到底
Can we win?
這場官司能打贏嗎？
The case happened on October 13, 2018.
案件是在 平成30年10月13日發生的
Mrs. Aso was out on that day
這天由於妻子不在
and the suspect, Shigeo Aso, was home alone.
只有嫌犯阿蘇重雄一人在家
SHIGEO ASO, THE ACCUSED
（被告，阿蘇重雄）
A fire broke out at 12 a.m.
凌晨十二點發生火災
Spray water on the house!
以房屋為中心灑水
Spray water towards the upper floor at the entrance!
從玄關處往二樓集中灑水
The fire was thought to be an accident at first,
當初推斷有可能是單純失火
but further investigation suggested the possibility of arson.
但卻在之後的調查中 發現了縱火的可能性
ARSON ACCIDENTAL FIRE
（縱火）
The police saw it as a crime committed for insurance money
警察認為 這是為了詐領保險金所犯的罪行
and arrested Shigeo Aso.
逮捕了阿蘇重雄
Aso confessed to the crime after his arrest.
被逮捕後，他承認了犯行
ACCOMPANYING DOCUMENTS
（供述筆錄）
Your husband turned himself in.
你先生承認了罪行啊？
Yes.
對
You were not at home on the day of the fire.
火災發生當天，你不在家是嗎？
Well, I have a disease,
我有些老毛病
so I stayed at the hospital for a check-up.
那天剛好住院檢查
But…
但是警方卻懷疑我
So they questioned you too?
所以警方也有跟你問話嗎？
This is embarrassing…
實在是羞於啟齒
but our family is in debt
但我們家背了一筆債
and they said it was the motive.
警方認為這就是犯案動機
Indeed, our life is tough.
實際上我們的生活確實是有點刻苦
SITE INSPECTION REPORT
（扣押物清單）
RECORD OF OBJECTS IN THE VICINITY
（物品）
But I just can't believe that
但是，我…
my husband would set our house on fire!
我真的無法相信 是外子放火燒了我們家
But…
話雖如此…
Indeed, if your husband had admitted he committed the crime…
的確，如果你先生 自己承認了犯行的話…
Oh, this.
對了，這個
They are Enterprise Sentai Salareader's
是《企業戰隊超人》的 課長黑戰士跟接待粉紅戰士吧？
-I like them too. -What?
-我也喜歡這個 -你說什麼啊？
They belonged to our son, who passed away five years ago.
這是我們五年前過世的兒子的遺物
They were the only ones my husband rescued from the fire.
火災時
What a pity.
真遺憾，我最喜歡加班紅戰士了
He was burned.
都燒掉了啊
Yes, all of them.
是的，全都燒掉了
-I'm sorry. -It's okay.
-很抱歉 -不
There you go.
請用
Sorry. Thank you.
真抱歉，謝謝
What are you going to do?
你打算怎麼做？
I don't know what I'll do yet.
我還不知道該怎麼做
I have to have an interview with Mr. Aso first.
得先跟本人接觸才知道
Tell me a rough plan, then.
至少也告訴我大致方針啊
I am your assistant. Against my will, though.
我可是黑川律師你的幫手 雖然不是自願的
I mean, the accused made a self-confession. In that case--
說來說去 被告都認罪了，既然如此…
The record was well-written, right?
那份筆錄寫得很好，對吧？
Did you also imagine what happened when you read it?
你看的時候也有畫面浮出腦海吧？
Imagine?
畫面？
How the accused set the house on fire
被告縱火後露出竊笑的表情
And it's…
那是…
We don't know if Mr. Shigeo Aso really did it or not yet,
我們還不清楚 這是否真的是阿蘇重雄的真正樣貌
so let's go and talk to him first.
所以首先就來問問他吧
I should've asked earlier,
雖然現在說有點遲了
but do you dress casually when you do an interview?
但你連跟當事人見面也這身裝扮啊？
I have only one suit.
我只有一套西裝而已
What about your backpack?
那這個背包呢？
It's convenient if anything happens.
有個萬一時這很方便的
-Convenient? -Yes.
-很方便？ -對
TOKYO DETENTION HOUSE
（東京看守所）
TAKU KUROKAWA - KAEDE WAKURA
（黑川拓律師）
Upon Mrs. Aso's request,
我是受你太太所託
I will be the new lawyer in charge of your case, Mr. Aso.
為阿蘇先生你辯護的律師
I have told the police and the prosecutor everything.
一切
You mean what you said in your self-confession was everything?
也就是說你自白的內容就是一切了？
Mr. Aso?
阿蘇先生？
-Mr. Kurokawa. -Your son's things…
-黑川律師 -你為什麼沒把令郎的遺物
Why didn't you take all of them with you?
全都拿出來呢？
His photo albums and clothes were burned too.
相簿跟衣服也都燒掉了對吧？
The Sentai heroes figures too, except Black and Pink,
戰隊超人的公仔也是
That again?
又要說這個啊？
If you had planned to set the house on fire,
若是預謀縱火
you should've been able to carry everything important with you.
應該早就把重要的東西 全都事前運走才對
Mr. Aso, did you really set the room on the first floor on fire…
阿蘇先生
as written in the statement?
在二樓的那個房間放火了嗎？
Did you set your late son
在過世的令郎
Yukio's room on fire?
幸雄小弟弟的房間放火了？
Of course I didn't.
怎麼可能？
The room was full of memories of our son.
在充滿兒子回憶的那個房間
Why would I set it on fire?
我怎麼可能在那裡縱火？
I told them that I didn't do it.
我一直堅持我沒做
Again…
說了好幾次
and again.
我都說了好幾次了
Only you were at the crime scene!
現場除了你以外沒別人了吧
We know you did it!
我很清楚你都做了些什麼
Hey, Aso, if you won't be honest with us,
要是你再不乖乖認罪
we'll arrest your wife too.
你的妻子也會被逮捕的
No! My wife's health is bad. Please don't do this.
這怎麼行？ 我太太身體不好，求求你了
If you talk to us honestly, we won't be unreasonable,
只要你乖乖坦承 我們也不會強人所難的
but…
但是嘛
if you still won't admit it,
要是你再這樣死不認罪
I'll really…
我就真的要…
I did it.
是我做的
I…
是我…
I set my house on fire.
放火燒了我家
Great. You finally admit it.
很好，總算認罪了啊
I'll take your statement, then.
那就要來寫筆錄了
So, how did you set it on fire?
所以呢？你是怎麼縱火的？
-How? -You committed the crime,
-怎麼縱火的？ -既然你是犯人
so, of course, you can say what you did.
當然有辦法交代犯行了
What did you do to help it burn, and where did you do it?
為了使火勢順利蔓延 是在哪裡，又是如何做的
Be specific.
說得具體點
I poured paraffin…
煤油…我灑了煤油
Where?
灑在哪裡？
Well, after our investigation,
不過，就調查結果來說
we found that setting fire on the ground floor
在一樓縱火是不會燒成那樣的
In that case,
那…
it's the bedroom on the first floor.
就在二樓寢室
But it's dangerous to set your own bedroom on fire.
在自己睡的房間放火未免也太危險了
Isn't it the room next to it?
不是隔壁房間嗎？
The room next to it? But it's…
隔壁？那房間是…
Your son's room, right?
是你兒子的房間吧？
You poured paraffin there and set it on fire.
你就是在那裡灑煤油放火的
I SET THE FIRE BY POURING OIL AROUND MY SON'S ROOM
（我在兒子的房間潑灑煤油縱火）
…for the insurance money.
為了詐取保險金
The police had decided
警方打從一開始
what I should say at the very beginning,
就幫我想好說辭了
then they just got me to sign the statement.
之後便逼著我簽署筆錄
That's awful!
太過分了，居然要人做假自白
Mr. Aso.
阿蘇先生
Please let me ask two questions.
請容我問你兩件事
Sure.
好的
One.
第一個問題是你受偵訊時的事
Of course.
當然了
Two.
第二個問題
Did you set your house on fire?
你有在自家縱火嗎？
I did not.
沒有
Okay, then.
我明白了
I'll investigate it thoroughly and defend you.
我會徹底調查，奮戰到底
As I thought, it's pretty damaged.
果然毀損得相當嚴重
It's been a long time since the fire.
畢竟火災後也過了一段時間
We're lucky it's still here.
光是建築物還留著就夠幸運了
-Let's go, then. -Okay.
-走吧 -好的
ENTRY FORBIDDEN
（禁止進入）
What? Hang on…
什麼？那個，請等一下…
-What? -Are we going inside?
-怎樣？ -該不會是要進去裡面吧？
Wait here if you don't want to get dirty.
你怕衣服弄髒就待在外面吧
Fine, I'll go! It's my job.
當然要進去了，這可是我的工作
The fire department thought
消防隊一開始推測 起火點是在一樓吧？
So it seems.
似乎是這樣
A heater in the Japanese-style room's cupboard
他們推測起火點在和室壁櫥裡的暖爐
The son's room was…
小孩房…
FLOOR PLAN
（二樓平面圖）
…right above the Japanese-style room?
是在和室的正上方啊
But why did the police suspect an arson?
但既然如此 警方為什麼又懷疑是縱火？
They even made Mr. Aso make a false self-confession.
甚至不惜 強迫阿蘇先生做出假的認罪自白
Because they made an assumption during the investigation.
因為這是推測搜查
The family was in debt, the house was on fire when Mr. Aso was alone,
因為這個家有負債 又是獨自在家時發生火災的
and they got the insurance money.
且成功申請保險金
It's fishy, so they assumed it was arson when they investigated it.
因為很可疑 於是以縱火為前提進行搜查
But this is absurd!
怎麼這樣？真亂來
It's too nasty!
未免太惡劣了吧
Nasty. But it's their job as well.
與其說惡劣 不如說這就是他們的義務
They're coming out!
出來了
What were you doing?
你們在做什麼？ 該不會是來拍靈異照片的吧？
A photo of the ghost?
靈異照片？
But nobody died in the house's fire.
這場火災沒有人死掉啊
-No, we mean Yukio! -Yukio?
-不是啦，我們是說幸雄 -幸雄？
My big sister said the house was burned because of Yukio's curse.
我姐姐說這間房子會燒起來 肯定是幸雄的詛咒
Yukio? Do you mean Yukio Aso, who used to live here?
幸雄？是以前 住在這裡的阿蘇幸雄嗎？
I don't know, but it really is cursed.
不知道，但詛咒真的存在
Boys, would you tell me that in more detail?
能請你們告訴我詳情嗎？
Would you like some snacks?
要吃零嘴嗎？
Here is our Human Kiosk.
出現了，一人超商
-What human kiosk? -Okay, here you go.
-那是什麼？ -拿去
It's Mr. Kurokawa's nickname.
黑川律師的綽號
His backpack is packed with various things.
他背包裡塞滿了各種東西
-The default items are snacks and drinks -What's this?
-基本上是零嘴跟飲料 -這什麼？
and it has toothbrushes, a nail clipper,
但也有牙刷、指甲剪
-spare underwear. -And this is…
-免洗褲 -還有呢…
Basically everything.
大致來說應有盡有
That doesn't make any sense.
真是莫名其妙
What kind of curse is it?
是怎樣的詛咒？
Various things. A few nights ago, our home--
有很多啊，上次晚上在家也…
Hey, what are you doing?
等等，你們在做什麼？
Mommy!
媽媽
Excuse me. We're lawyers investigating the fire here.
不好意思 我們是律師，正在調查這起火災
Lawyers? The Aso family's?
律師？是阿蘇太太找來的？
Yes, we are.
是的
In that case, will you tell them
那能請各位轉告她嗎？
to tidy up here before they get a lawyer for the criminal husband?
在幫縱火的老公找律師之前 先把這裡整理好
Our children try to go in and it's dangerous.
孩子們都想跑進去，很危險的
Lately, this area has been dangerous enough already.
最近本來治安就夠差的了
Come on. Let's go.
好了，回家吧
Let's go.
來
It was reported in the news, so we're criticized for it.
畢竟都上新聞了 看來也受到不少責難啊
Yeah.
是啊
I wonder what the curse is.
到底是什麼詛咒呢？
I think it's here.
那就是這裡吧？
Okay.
對
PICTURE 23
（圖23）
Mr. Kurokawa, I did some digging about Yukio Aso.
黑川律師 我調查到阿蘇幸雄小弟弟的事了
Oh, thank you.
謝謝
Yukio? Why did you check him out?
幸雄小弟弟的事？為什麼要調查他？
Because I don't know what the key to solving the case is.
或許會成為解決案件的關鍵啊
Found it. This one too.
對了，還有這個
It's the video taken by a spectator during the fire of Aso's house.
這是一個看熱鬧的民眾 在阿蘇家火災發生時拍的
Wow, that's helpful!
幫我大忙了
It isn't for free, of course.
當然不是免費的
Let me interview you. It's give and take.
交換條件是讓我採訪
Kurokawa, using the press can be one of the tactics.
黑川，利用報導也是戰略之一喔
Okay.
好的
All right, then. Please.
我明白了，請給我
-Yes!
-很好… -很好
Yukio Aso. Died aged ten five years ago in 2014.
阿蘇幸雄 在五年前2014年去世，當時十歲
He had a congenital heart defect
他的心臟有先天性疾患
and had had two surgeries when he was two years and ten months old.
出生後十個月跟兩歲時 共動了兩次手術
It was the reason that the Aso couple was in debt.
阿蘇夫妻的負債似乎就是因此而來的
So, Yukio died of the disease?
所以幸雄小弟弟是因病過世的了？
No, the reason was this.
不，這才是原因
CHILD KILLED IN A FIRE AT AN EMPTY FACTORY
（廢棄工廠火災，一名兒童身亡）
"Empty factory"?
“廢棄工廠火災”？
It's still at the place 200 meters away from Aso's house.
該處距離阿蘇家200公尺 遺跡現在也還留存著
Some children played with fireworks and caused the fire.
似乎是孩子們玩煙火引發的火災
Only Yukio didn't escape in time and suffocated in the smoke.
只有幸雄小弟弟來不及逃而被捲入
This is heartbreaking.
那還真讓人心痛啊
So the children said it was cursed
所以孩子們說的詛咒
because Yukio died in a fire?
是因為幸雄小弟弟死於火災嗎？
Hang on… This isn't right!
不…這未免太怪了
How can the fire five years ago be related to this fire?
五年前的火災 跟這次哪會有什麼關係？
Well, you're right.
這倒是沒錯
We can't use this information to plead extenuating circumstances!
我們又不是 要用這個情報要求情狀減刑
Aren't we going to argue that the police forced him
而是針對警方 強迫當事人做出假自白提告吧？
It's one of the points, of course.
這當然也是重點之一
So, we should give a flat denial when we defend, right?
那就是採取完全否認的辯護方針了吧
If the confession isn't reliable,
只要動搖了自白的可信性 接著只要直攻狀況證據就…
We will certainly lose.
肯定會輸
-What? -Miss Wakura,
-什麼？ -和倉律師
you can't tackle a criminal case in such a straightforward way.
刑事案沒這麼簡單
We don't have enough material to defend him yet.
為了辯護，我們目前手邊的牌還不夠
But we have to do the pre-trial conference procedure soon.
但是，公判前整理程序 馬上就要到了啊
You guys are working.
大家都在忙啊
Oh, Mr. Beppu. Good afternoon.
所長，辛苦了
-Good afternoon.
-辛苦了
Is it the arson case?
是那起縱火案嗎？
What's the chance of winning?
勝算如何？
I don't know. I have to go and inspect some more.
還不清楚，還得繼續檢證才行
Don't be too hard on us.
還請手下留情
Oh, Miss Wakura, do you have a minute?
對了，和倉律師，能耽誤一下嗎？
Yes.
是
You want me to spy on Mr. Kurokawa?
監視？要我監視黑川律師嗎？
Yes. This might be a false charge, right?
對，這起案件很可能是冤案吧？
In that case, Kurokawa will surely do something reckless to win.
這麼一來 黑川肯定會為了贏而不擇手段
And he'll spend lots of money and effort to do so.
而且還不惜花錢費工
People in charge of criminal cases don't care about profit,
負責刑事案的傢伙都不在乎利益的
so we want you to spy on him and stop him from losing control.
所以希望你能幫忙監視 阻止他們亂來
But how can I stop him?
這…就算要我阻止也…
If you do your job successfully,
要是你能好好勝任
we might transfer you to our corporate law division.
我打算把你調到企業法務部門
We can let you be a large company's consultant too.
讓你擔任大企業的法律顧問
But I shouldn't obstruct Mr. Kurokawa's work.
但是我不能妨礙黑川律師工作啊
I didn't tell you to obstruct it.
不會要你妨礙他的
I only want him to work sensibly as a lawyer.
只是希望你 能讓他進行符合常理的辯護行為
Kurokawa and Mr. Yufuin pay too much attention to false charges
黑川跟湯布院律師太過執著於冤案了
and they criticize the police and public prosecutors too much.
對於警方或檢方總是過於批判
Japan's police and prosecutors are capable.
日本的警方跟檢方都很優秀的
They don't get a nearly 100% conviction rate for nothing.
有罪率近乎百分之百 可不是隨便說說的
Even if you fight against them,
就算跟他們爭
as a result, it isn't going to benefit the accused.
到頭來對被告也沒好處
Perhaps that's the case, but…
或許是這樣沒錯，可是…
Don't worry.
沒問題的
Your reputation won't get worse even if you lose.
就算官司打輸了 你的評價也不會變差的
it would be because you can't stop Mr. Kurokawa losing control.
若是變差也只會是因為 你沒能阻止黑川律師亂來
RINTARO IBUSUKI, PUBLIC PROSECUTOR
（指宿林太郎 東京地方檢察廳檢察官）
Ibusuki.
指宿
Good afternoon, sir.
辛苦了
COURTHOUSE
（法院）
PRE-TRIAL CONFERENCE PROCEDURE
（公判前整理程序）
PROCEDURE TO NARROW DOWN THE NUMBER OF ISSUES
（為使審判順利進行）
TO ENSURE A SMOOTH ADJUDICATION
（確定爭議點的程序）
-Oh gosh. I really can't do it. -Can't do what?
-果然還是不行 -什麼？
I really hate how it makes me feel like it's strangling me.
我很受不了這種脖子被綁住的感覺
Endure it.
你就忍一下吧
Anyway, is it okay?
-比起這個，你沒問題吧？ -這種正式服裝很不舒服啊
I'm not asking that. I mean how you'll defend our client.
誰管你這個啊？我是在問辯護方針
How likely will we win when we confront the prosecutor?
要是跟檢方全面對決，你有勝算嗎？
I have no idea yet.
這我還不知道
We're here already but you still don't know?
事到如今還說不知道？
Good afternoon, Mr. Kurokawa.
辛苦了，黑川律師
Hello.
你好
You are a new lawyer, right? I'm the public prosecutor, Ibusuki.
你帶了個新面孔呢，我是檢察官指宿
I am Wakura.
敝姓和倉
Please go easy on me, Mr. Kurokawa.
還請手下留情，黑川律師
You've made me go through many bitter experiences.
畢竟我們吃過你不少虧
Right judgment is more important than winning or losing.
比起輸贏 做出正確判決才是最重要的吧
You are right. Let's both do our best.
沒錯，彼此都全力以赴吧
By the way, I just ran into your father after some time.
話說回來，剛才久違地見到了令尊呢
Did you?
是嗎？
He's concerned about your future.
他很擔心你的前途
You'd better not make him too worried.
還是別讓他太擔心吧
Sorry to have kept you waiting.
久等了
Let's start now.
那麼就馬上開始吧
Yukio.
幸雄
I'm sorry.
對不起
COURTHOUSE
（法院）
Please uncuff him.
請解除手銬
"On October 13, 2018, at around midnight,
“被告於平成30年 10月13日午夜零時
at 20-8, Nishimachi 2-chome, Edogawa City,
在江戶川區西町
a wooden house with tile roofing owned by the accused,
於被告所有的木造瓦片宅邸二樓房間
lit it with a match, and set the house on fire.
並持火柴縱火
As a result, the house the accused and his family lived in
結果造成被告與家屬
The charge and punitive article
罪名與刑罰
is Arson of Inhabited Buildings, Article 108."
將依循刑法第108條 放火燒燬現住建築物”
Accused.
被告
In the bill of indictment read by the public prosecutor,
檢察官剛才宣讀的 起訴狀內容是否有誤？
Everything was wrong.
全都是錯的
-Really? -Seriously?
-真的假的啊？ -都是錯的？
I did not set my house on fire.
我並沒有在自家放火
All of that is false.
這全是一派胡言
WITNESS WAITING ROOM
（證人等候室）
Witness, please answer my questions with "yes" or "no".
請證人以“是”或“不是” 回答我的問題
Yes.
好的
DEFENSE'S QUESTIONING
（辯護方詢問證人）
This case was constructed using only circumstantial evidence.
本案件僅以狀況證據架構而成
The police coerced my client into giving a self-confession as evidence
被告供稱其自白是遭警察強迫寫下的
This is not true at all.
完全沒這回事
-The accused himself-- -Excuse me.
-這是被告擅自… -抱歉
I said this at the beginning.
我一開始已經說過了 請以“是”或“不是”回答
Yes.
是
Did you say to my client that if he wouldn't make a confession honestly,
你似乎對被告說了 “若不乖乖自白就逮捕你的妻子”
Is that true?
這是事實嗎？
No.
不是
You said that!
明明就有說
He definitely said it. The look on his face told us.
絕對有說，看臉就知道了
At first, the oral statement stated that he set fire with a lighter,
供述筆錄的最前面 寫了是用打火機點火
but it changed to a match later.
但後來又換成火柴
Don't you find it strange?
不覺得這很奇怪嗎？
All suspects change their statement out of guilt,
嫌犯總是容易 因為罪惡感而不斷改變供述
but I kept talking to him patiently. As a result,
即使如此，因為有好好面對了
he told me that he felt a weight was lifted off his shoulders
最後總是會說“總算能鬆口氣了”
and even thanked me.
甚至說出道謝的話呢
Please answer "yes" or "no".
請回答“是”或“不是”
Yes. I mean…
是，我是說…
No.
不是
My client was burned,
被告不惜被燒傷
but he still carried his late son's things out from the house.
也堅持從火災現場 拿出已故兒子的遺物
Isn't this and setting the house on fire contradictory?
這個行為跟在兒子房間 放火的行為不是自相矛盾嗎？
It isn't.
不會啊，我反而認為 這是故意要引發同情
and deceive us, that he didn't commit a crime.
好隱瞞自己犯罪事實的卑鄙想法
Witness, I repeat--
證人，我再說一次…
Well, five years have passed since his son died,
畢竟都死了五年了
so he must have wanted money more than the memory of his son.
比起和孩子的回憶 他肯定更想要錢吧
He just brought the rubbish out for a show.
還拿那種破爛玩意出來現
Don't be ridiculous!
別開玩笑了
Shigeo!
老公
What do you know about me?
你到底懂我什麼了？
-Do you know how I felt at that time? -Please stop.
-你懂那時的我抱著什麼心情嗎？ -請住手
-Take it back! -Please calm down.
-給我收回那句話 -冷靜點
How dare you make a fool of me!
開什麼玩笑
-Stop it. -Be quiet!
-別這樣 -肅靜
-Take it back! Take it back!
-給我收回那句話…
Take it back!
你給我收回那句話
TOKYO DETENTION HOUSE
（東京看守所）
Why did you do that?
為什麼要那麼做？
He obviously provoked you.
那很明顯是在挑釁你啊
He did it to make you angry and give the lay judges a bad impression.
為了激怒你，好讓裁判員的印象變差
I am sorry.
很抱歉
But I couldn't keep quiet.
但我真的無法默不吭聲
He made me feel that my son's feelings were trampled on.
他這是在踐踏我對孩子的心意
I know how you feel,
我明白你的心情
but calm down a little, or in the trial, you'll--
但還是請你冷靜點，不然這場官司…
I don't mind even if we lose.
輸了也無所謂
Mr. Aso.
阿蘇先生
I was told during the questioning
偵訊時對方也這麼跟我說
that my lawyer can only plead extenuating circumstances.
律師只能幫忙減輕刑責
I have to go to prison anyway, so I shouldn't fight back needlessly.
無論怎樣都會坐牢 要我別做無謂的抵抗
Gosh.
怎麼這樣？
Mr. Aso, if you give up, there is no way we can defend you.
要是阿蘇先生你都放棄了
If you're convicted guilty in the trial,
要是確定被判有罪
they will make you setting Yukio's room on fire a fact.
你在幸雄房間縱火的事 就會被當成事實了
In that case…
既然如此
it must be God's punishment.
那就是所謂的天譴了吧
God's punishment?
天譴？
Because in the end…
因為到頭來…
I couldn't protect Yukio.
我還是沒能守護幸雄
My husband,
外子這五年以來
he always felt guilty about Yukio.
一直對幸雄的事懷抱著罪惡感
Even though he passed away in an accident?
是指他意外過世一事嗎？
Our son was born weak.
他出生身體就不好
He couldn't make friends easily because of that.
因為這樣
Our son was bullied at school.
那孩子在學校遭受了霸凌
Hang on a second.
請等一下
That means only Yukio couldn't escape
那廢棄工廠的火災 只有幸雄來不及逃是因為…
I don't want to talk about that again after all these years.
事到如今 我們也不想再追究這件事了
It's just…
我跟外子…
we were so angry at ourselves that we didn't realize how Yukio felt!
只是對於自己 沒能察覺到幸雄內心的痛苦
We couldn't
我們…
protect our son.
沒能守護那孩子
Mrs. Aso.
阿蘇太太
Children don't want to make their parents worry too,
孩子們也有自己的尊嚴
It isn't because you and Mr. Aso didn't realize,
不是兩位沒能察覺
it's because Yukio tried very hard
而是他努力不讓兩位察覺
to hide it from you.
我認為幸雄一定是這樣想的
I have a son too.
因為我也有個兒子
Mr. Kurokawa.
黑川律師
Can we win the case?
這場官司能打贏嗎？
I don't know.
我不知道
Mr. Kurokawa.
黑川律師
But…
但是…
We will do our best.
我會盡最大的努力
This is the burnt remains of the beam between
這是一、二樓之間
the ground and first floor.
梁柱燒毀剩下的部分
As you can see,
如各位所見
the edges of the upper side of the beam were burned and rounded off
梁上方的角被燒成圓角
but the bottom side wasn't.
下面卻沒有這現象
BEAM
（梁柱）
The beam is usually attached closely to the floor of the first floor,
一般而言，梁柱會緊貼二樓地板
so there is no gap for air to go in
所以不會有空氣進入
and the beam's upper part couldn't have been burned like that.
不可能把梁柱上方燒成這樣
From this, we can see that the fire broke out on the first floor,
從這跡象看來也可得知起火點在二樓
and this is the truth, without a doubt.
是不爭的事實
Thank you, Professor Totsukawa.
謝謝十津川教授
As you have heard, according to the expert's analysis,
如各位聽到的，根據專家分析
ORIGIN OF FIRE, CHILD'S BEDROOM
（起火點，小孩房）
The defense lawyer claims that
而辯護方主張失火是由
the heater in the ground floor's Japanese-style room caused the fire.
一樓和室壁櫥裡的暖爐所引起
Indeed, perhaps the fire broke out on the first floor as well,
的確，一樓或許也有起火
but it happened after the accused set fire on the first floor
但這可推測是在二樓縱火後
and he also set fire on the ground floor as a deception.
再轉向一樓縱火進行偽裝
Deception?
偽裝？
It happened in a residential area.
現場是住宅區
Fortunately, the fire didn't spread to the surrounding area,
幸好沒有延燒到周圍
but it could have caused a horrible tragedy too.
不然很可能會引發大慘劇
Committing such a vicious crime like this
為了詐欺保險金的自私動機 引發這種危險犯罪
is definitely unacceptable.
決不可輕饒
I've finished.
以上
ENTRY FORBIDDEN
（禁止進入）
Indeed. The upper side is burnt.
真的耶，是上面燒焦了
Did you come a long way to verify that?
你只是為了確認這個而特地跑一趟？
You took many photos the other day.
上次不是才拍了一堆照片嗎？
Sorry, I thought checking the place in its original state
抱歉，我想說在現場 確認原本狀況更能當參考
I said original state, but it's burnt.
說是原本狀況 但這根本也都燒過了嘛
It isn't funny at all!
一點也不好笑
I was curious the other day too.
上次我也很好奇
What on earth is this?
這到底是什麼呢？
I don't know, and I think it isn't going to help.
不知道，知道了應該也一樣沒意義
That reminds me.
對了
Here you go.
來，請吃吧
Have some. You seem annoyed.
你看起來好像很煩躁，吃吧
But you won't try not to annoy me?
能請你別讓我更煩躁了嗎？
Okay. Let's go to the next destination, then.
我明白了，那去下個地點吧
Next?
下個地點？
The empty factory. The one that Yukio died at five years ago.
廢棄工廠 五年前幸雄小弟弟過世的地方
Why are we going there?
到底為什麼要去啊？
PRIVATE PROPERTY - KEEP OUT
（私人土地，禁止進入）
Can we go inside?
進不去嗎？
It's against the law.
擅闖就犯法了
But someone had been inside.
但裡面看起來有人進去過的痕跡啊
Even so, it's still against the law!
即使如此也是違法行為吧
Maybe it's got a secret path over there?
那邊是不是有祕道能進去？
It is still against the law, even if there is!
就算有祕道也一樣違法啊
Gosh!
等等…
It's a magazine.
這是彈匣呢
Some people probably played airsoft nearby.
應該是有人在這裡玩WG
"Airsoft"?
WG？
Yes, airsoft. There are BBs on the ground.
就是生存遊戲 地上也有散落的BB彈
That reminds me.
話說回來 有馬小姐給我的火災現場影片
people in military outfits were among the spectators.
看熱鬧的人裡面也有穿迷彩服的人呢
So, they were playing airsoft here?
原來是在這裡打啊
Is it a Colt Government?
是M1911手槍嗎？
What's the matter?
怎麼了？
What does it have to do with the trial?
這跟官司到底有什麼關連？
Nothing. Maybe--
或許沒有吧
Mr. Kurokawa.
黑川律師
Forget your pride and reputation.
何不拋下尊嚴跟世人的看法 現在轉成情狀辯護呢？
What?
什麼？
Mr. Aso was forced to make a false confession,
假自白的事使阿蘇先生失控 已經給法官留下壞印象了
The analysis of the fire given by the prosecutor was hard to refute.
檢方也拿出了 難以反駁的火災鑑定結果
We'll surely lose at this rate!
這樣下去絕對會輸的
We should try to reduce the sentence--
-既然如此，至少讓刑責減輕… -這麼一來
it means we admit that Mr. Aso set the child's bedroom on fire.
就代表我們承認 他在自己兒子的房間縱火的事了
Miss Wakura, I thought you believed what Mr. Aso said.
和倉律師 你不相信阿蘇先生的話嗎？
I believe him!
當然相信了 我也聽到他對幸雄小弟弟的思念
-But even so-- -I see.
-但即使如此… -這樣啊
Indeed. You must be annoyed if you believe him.
既然相信，確實是會很煩躁
What do you mean?
這是什麼意思？
Mr. Kurokawa, do you not trust Mr. Aso?
黑川律師，你不相信阿蘇先生嗎？
I don't know because I didn't see the scene of the fire.
我不知道，我並沒有目睹現場
What?
什麼？那你為什麼還接下這案子 幫他做完全否認的辯護？
Because Mr. Aso said he didn't do it.
因為阿蘇先生說他沒做啊
What you say doesn't make sense.
我實在不懂你在說什麼
Why do you make assumptions?
為什麼能斷言這就是事實？
What?
什麼？
They are in debt, there was a fire, and they got the insurance money,
負債，發生火災後收到保險金
so the police assumed that Mr. Aso set his house on fire.
所以就斷言是他自己縱火的
Mr. Aso loves his son and he said he didn't do it,
這跟聽到他愛孩子並否認犯行
so you assumed that he really didn't.
就斷言他沒做不是一樣嗎？
Well…
這…
I don't know if it's true.
我不知道
That's why I'm investigating it.
所以才要調查
You won't go inside?
你不進去嗎？
You shouldn't. It's against the law.
這可不行，是違法行為呢
Did it really happen like that?
會變那樣嗎？
Good afternoon. You've got a parcel.
辛苦了，有東西送來了
Thank you. Mr. Kurokawa, it's your parcel.
謝謝，黑川律師，那個東西來了
Oh, thanks.
不好意思
What is that?
那是什麼？
We asked Mrs. Aso to send us Yukio's things that weren't burned.
我們請阿蘇太太 把幸雄小弟弟沒被燒掉的遺物送來了
I'm so glad they weren't seized.
幸好沒被扣押
What's the point of checking them?
確認這種東西幹嘛？
What's the matter, Miss Wakura?
怎麼了，和倉律師？
Nothing.
沒什麼，我只是不覺得 黑川律師有打算要認真辯護
What the heck?!
什麼跟什麼啊？
Think whatever you want, but Mr. Kurokawa--
你怎麼想跟黑川律師…
Wait a second.
等等
What's that smell?
這味道是什麼？
-What do we do? -Oh no!
-怎麼回事？ -糟糕
-What should we do? -What are you doing?
-怎麼辦？ -你在做什麼啊，黑川律師？
-The fire extinguisher!
-快拿滅火器 -滅火器…
What… Hey…
什麼？喂…
-Oh no, oh no! -Kurokawa!
-糟了… -黑川
Seriously?
不是吧？
-No… -Hey!
-不行… -喂
-Fire extinguisher! -Hey…
-等等… -快拿滅火器
-Oh no… -Don't mind that! Put out the fire!
-糟了 -比起這個，快點滅火啊
-Found it! -Get the fire extinguisher!
-有了 -快拿滅火器
-Hurry up! -The fire extinguisher!
-快點 -是
-The fire extinguisher! Hurry up! -Yes!
-快拿滅火器 -來了
-Go…! -Put it out!
-快滅火… -快點
He wanted to check whether the fire really burned
他似乎是想確認火的燃燒方式
in the way the public prosecutor claimed,
是否正如檢方所說
so he used a miniature to do it.
而用了迷你模型來確認
He had to do it indoors? This is crazy.
居然在室內做這種事？簡直是瘋了
So, why isn't the culprit, Kurokawa, here?
所以呢？黑川主犯怎麼沒來？
The evidence can't get wet,
因為現場有不能淋濕的證據物 他正在確認是否有耗損
Blimey, he's giving me a headache!
真傷腦筋啊
He isn't likely to win the trial too, right?
官司看起來也沒勝算吧？
You can plead extenuating circumstances
要不就轉求情狀減刑 要不也能中途抽手
What do you think, Miss Wakura?
和倉律師，你覺得呢？
I have no idea.
問我也沒用啊
Anyway, you guys will clean up the mess.
總之，請各位一起幫忙清掃
-Okay.
-是
I am counting on you to do your job properly, Miss Wakura.
這之後也請你用心協助了，和倉律師
Okay.
是
Mr. Kurokawa is as reckless as always.
黑川律師還是一樣亂來啊
He can't see his surroundings when he works on a case.
在處理辯護案時 他總是不會注意到其他事物
Does Mr. Kurokawa always do this?
黑川律師總是這樣嗎？
"This"? What exactly do you want to ask?
“這樣”是哪樣？
He is always like this.
他一直都是這樣
He isn't happy until he checks everything himself.
不全部自己調查清楚就是不服氣
Let's clean the place.
繼續打掃吧
Okay.
是
In Japan, if you're prosecuted for a crime,
在日本只要被以刑事事件起訴
there's a nearly 100% chance that you'll be found guilty.
幾乎是百分之百確定有罪
That's exactly why pleading extenuating circumstances
所以主攻情狀減刑
is one of the strategies too.
也是一種戰略
But if the person wasn't caught red-handed,
但只要不是現行犯
there must be a blank that the lawyer has to investigate.
就一定會有律師非得親自調查的空白
Blank?
空白？
If you assume you know what happened without checking,
不經調查就推測斷定
it's the same as taking part in a false charge.
就等於是冤案的幫凶
Mr. Kurokawa still hasn't returned?
黑川律師還沒好嗎？
It annoys me that the man who caused the fire isn't cleaning the place.
造成這一團亂的當事人 卻不來打掃，也太讓人火大了
Indeed.
就是說啊
I'll call him here.
我去叫他
CHRISTMAS 2013
（2013年聖誕節）
Mr. Kurokawa, you should be responsible for what you did--
黑川律師，自己做的事至少負點責任
Miss Wakura.
和倉律師
It's the curse.
是詛咒
Yes?
什麼？
The curse… Probably. In other words…
-就是詛咒…也就是說… -等等
-Where are you going? -See you!
-你要去哪？ -黑川出發了
Mr. Kurokawa?
黑川律師
Wait! Where are you going?
等等，你要去哪裡？
You should tell me now!
你好歹也說明一下啊
Huh?
什麼？
Wait!
等等
Yes?
是誰？
I'm Kurokawa, a lawyer. We met the other day.
我是律師黑川 前幾天見過面，總之我想確認一件事
-Check something? -It's very important. Please.
-總之？ -是很重要的事，拜託了
Mr. Kurokawa! What do you want to check?
黑川律師，你要確認什麼啊？
-Yes? -Sorry to bother you.
-你好 -抱歉突然來訪
-Your son-- -Mom, hurry up!
-請問令郎… -媽媽，快點啦
-Excuse me. -Hey!
-不好意思 -這是怎樣？我要報警了
Please don't call the police!
請千萬不要報警
-Sorry for coming suddenly. -Who are you?
-抱歉突然跑進來 -你是誰？
Lawyer. We met the other day.
我是律師，上次有見過面的啊
Please tell me about Yukio's curse.
我想請你告訴我幸雄的詛咒是什麼
TOUO UNIVERSITY
（東央大學）
-Excuse me. Where are we now? -The university's corridor.
-請問這裡是哪裡啊？ -大學走廊
I know that, but why are we at a university?
這我當然知道 為什麼大家要一起來大學？
Follow me and you'll know.
跟著走就知道了
-Zoom in a bit more. -Okay.
-攝影機再靠近點 -好
Keep going.
再靠近點
-All right.
-好，沒問題了 -是
-Set up Camera B now. -Okay.
-接著換B攝影機
Hello, Miss Arima.
有馬小姐，你好
-Hello.
-辛苦了
-Where is Dr. Akiu? -Working.
-秋保先生呢？ -正在工作中
That guy is as unfriendly to me as always.
那男人對我還是一樣冷漠
Dr. Akiu, thank you for today too.
秋保先生，今天也請多指教了
It's ready. Let's start now.
都準備好了，馬上就開始
Okay.
是
I haven't seen you before.
沒見過你啊
This is Miss Wakura. She just joined us.
這位是新來的和倉律師
This is Touo University's Physics Department's associate professor,
這位是東央大學
I'm Wakura. Nice to meet you.
敝姓和倉，初次見面
You don't look like a lawyer. I thought you were a student.
看起來不像律師，我還以為是學生呢
Yes? I am 26 years old already.
-嗯？別看我這樣，我已經26歲了 -不
Let's begin.
那要開始了
What's wrong with him?
那個人是怎樣？
Don't worry about it. He's always like that.
別放在心上，他就是這樣
Anyway, what is he going to start doing here?
話說要開始，是要做什麼啊？
TOUO UNIVERSITY
（東央大學）
Kurokawa will surely do something reckless to win.
黑川肯定會為了贏而不擇手段
So, we want you to spy on him and stop him from losing control.
所以希望你能幫忙監視 阻止他們亂來
Is this what "lose control" means?
亂來就是指這個嗎？
Experiment?
實驗？
Why did that happen?
怎麼會變這樣？
He did it himself and didn't tell me.
他完全沒說明就著手進行了
Stop him now! Even if you have to risk your life!
現在就阻止他 不惜拼上性命也要阻止他
Risk my life?
居然要我拼了命阻止？
I can't possibly stop this!
根本不可能阻止啊
COURTHOUSE
（法院）
Defense lawyer, please do your cross-examination.
辯護方請進行反對詢問
Yes, Your Honor.
是
Regarding the testimony you gave last time,
根據上次證詞的內容 我想再確認一次
The upper side of the beam was burned and rounded off
梁柱上方角被燒成圓角
but the bottom wasn't.
下面卻沒有
If the beam is attached closely to the floor of the first floor,
這是因為梁柱跟二樓地板完全貼合
this cannot happen because there is no gap for air to go in.
所以不會有空氣
the beam won't be in this condition.
是不會變這樣的
Are you sure about that?
確定沒錯嗎？
Yes, I'm sure about it.
對，肯定沒錯
Sorry, I would like to ask again.
很抱歉，我再問一次
Air can't go in because there isn't a gap.
是因為沒有縫隙 所以沒有空氣進入的空間
-Is that what you say? -You are very annoying.
-是這樣沒錯吧？ -你還真煩人啊
Even an assistant at my university knows that.
在我任教的大學 連助手也知道，這可是常識
What if between the beam and the floor of the first floor
那麼如果梁柱跟二樓地板間
there is a tiny gap?
有著些微的縫隙呢？
A gap?
縫隙？
That's impossible.
這種事怎麼可能？
I am asking what if there is?
只是假設而已
If there really is one,
若真有縫隙
fire could go up through the gap from the ground floor too.
從一樓開始燒的火 也有可能燒進那個縫隙裡
But it's pointless to make such an assumption.
不過這也只是毫無意義的假設
Thank you.
謝謝
Your Honor,
審判長 請讓我出示辯方第32號證據
The image has been
這圖像已經認可
This is the plan of Mr. Aso's house, which was burned down in the fire.
這是因火災而燒毀的阿蘇宅邸設計圖
It was kept in the architectural firm that designed the house.
這是當初負責設計的 建築事務所保存的備份
Please have a look at this part.
請看這裡
This construction material is called a joist.
這是建築材料，稱為托梁
It was put between the beam and the floor
是用來補強 梁柱與二樓地板之間的建材
Joist?
托梁？
There was a gap.
藉由這個托梁
Because there were joists,
梁柱跟二樓地板之間 會有兩公分的縫隙
I verified with the contractor and at the scene.
我跟施工業者確認過了
I found the burnt remains of what should've been a joist.
現場也發現了 推測為托梁的燃燒遺留物
Next, this has been accepted as special additional evidence too.
接著也是經認可的追加證據調查
I would like to question Touo University Physics Department's
我請來了東央大學理工學部物理學科
First, please have a look at defense evidence number 33.
首先請看 辯方第33號證據的檢證影片
In the experiment,
在這場實驗裡 我們盡可能精巧重現了
in as much detail as possible.
二樓建築宅邸的一部分
As you can see, fire enters the gap resulting from the joists
如各位所見 托梁處造成的縫隙會引火
and heated the upper part of the beam.
讓梁柱從上方加熱燃燒
And this is the condition of the beam after the experiment.
而這就是實驗後梁柱的狀態
BEAM
（梁柱）
FIRE DAMAGED SURFACE AREA - BEAM
（遭燒毀的表面積）
In other words, even if the fire only broke out on the ground floor,
也就是說，就算是一樓失火
the result would be the same as what the prosecutor showed us?
也能跟檢方得到同一個結果？
As you have seen.
就如各位所見
Objection.
我有異議
-What's the point of that? -You mean…
-這事實又有什麼意義？ -你的意思是…
The defense only showed
辯方只是指出就算是一樓失火 也能將梁柱燒成相同樣子
but didn't disprove that the fire broke out on the first floor.
並非否定起火點是二樓
It also didn't prove that the heater on the ground floor caused the fire.
此外，也沒有實證 能證明是一樓暖爐造成失火
You are right.
你說的沒錯
Therefore, we did an experiment to prove it.
所以，我們實際做了驗證
The heater is the same model as the one found at the scene of fire.
此為跟案發現場相同型號的暖爐
We'll now make it light up automatically.
我現在就讓它自行點火
Why?
怎麼會？
When a strong electromagnetic wave of a certain frequency
這是因特定周波數 造成強力電波，使機器偶然啟動
a heater in this case, it causes the heater to turn on by mistake.
這次的情況 則是因此讓暖爐自動錯誤啟動了
This heater isn't remote-controlled,
這種暖爐雖然不是遙控式
but if you press the button, the electronic circuit inside
卻是按下按鈕 就能啟動當中電路而點火的構造
Therefore, interference by unlicensed radio signals outside
因此若有違法電波從外部造成干擾
can light it like this.
就有可能像這樣點火
Unlicensed radio signals? Was anything found near the scene?
違法電波？現場哪裡有了？
The transceiver used in airsoft was found.
是在生存遊戲裡使用的無線電
On the day of the accident, at the empty factory nearby,
案發當天，現場附近的廢棄工廠
some young people were playing airsoft.
有一群年輕人在玩生存遊戲
It was unauthorized, that is, the so-called "field airsoft".
似乎是未經許可的野戰生存遊戲
Electromagnetic waves emitted by the high output transceiver they used
而他們使用的 高輸出無線電電波就讓暖爐點火了
Similar happenings were observed in my client's neighborhood
這現象也在被告自宅周遭發生
but were treated as an anomalous phenomenon.
似乎一直被當成某種靈異現象
Yukio's curse?
幸雄的詛咒？
The house was burned because of Yukio's curse.
這間房子會燒起來肯定是幸雄的詛咒
Please tell me about Yukio's curse.
我想請你告訴我幸雄的詛咒是什麼
It happens at night.
晚上就會發生
The TV switches on and off by itself.
電視會突然自己開開關關的
At the same time when the fire broke out,
發生火災的同一時間
some young people were playing airsoft at the empty factory.
在廢棄工廠 玩生存遊戲的青年們的證詞
I have their testimonies and those given by the witnesses there.
跟周遭目擊相同情況的人們的證詞
Kurokawa, can I go now?
黑川，可以了嗎？
Thank you, Professor.
謝謝
Prosecution, would you like to do any cross-examination?
檢方，要進行反對詢問嗎？
You considered only the police's and the prosecutor's investigation
警察只以檢方搜查為根據
and didn't take into account all kinds of possibilities.
而不考慮到各種可能性
You used a poor experiment done by an assistant
只讓比學生好一點的助手去做
who is no better than a student as evidence.
還堅持這種不充分的檢證
Someone like that
這樣的人
can't even call himself a scientist.
根本不能說是科學研究者
It seems the same thing happened before your son died too.
這次的現象 在令郎生前似乎也曾發生過
What?
什麼？
The empty factory that was burned
發生火災的廢棄工廠
was still running six months before Yukio passed away.
直到幸雄小弟弟 過世的半年前似乎都還在運作
Lorries that went in and out there also used unlicensed radio signals.
在那裡出入的卡車 似乎也利用了非法無線電
CHRISTMAS 2013
（2013年聖誕節）
This is the video tape that Mr. Aso managed to bring out from the fire.
這是阿蘇先生 從火災裡搶救下來的錄影帶
Please have a look.
請看
Yes!
太好了
This is Yukio's Christmas present!
沒錯，這就是幸雄的聖誕禮物
Do you like it? Are you happy?
怎麼樣？開心嗎？
Yes. Thank you, Dad!
開心，謝謝爸爸
It's lovely, isn't it?
真是太好了呢
Oh? The heater turned on by itself again.
怪了，暖爐又自己點燃了
Really?
真的嗎？是壞掉了嗎？
All right.
好了
My classmates say things at their homes do that sometimes too.
班上同學家裡偶爾也會發生這種事呢
They said the things were haunted or cursed.
大家都說是被幽靈之類的詛咒了
That's scary!
那還真可怕呢
But I'm not scared because you'll protect me, Dad.
一點也不可怕，因為我有爸爸保護
Mr. Aso.
阿蘇先生
Among the memories of you and Yukio,
你拼命地想守住的
and risked your life to protect…
跟幸雄小弟弟的回憶之中
there was the evidence that could prove your innocence.
就有洗清你冤罪的證據
Yukio!
幸雄
The inadequate investigation
警方、檢方
done by the police and the public prosecutor…
不充分的搜查跟檢證
had caused my client and his wife tremendous mental distress.
給被告與家人帶來嚴重的精神傷害
Also, it almost ruined the bond…
甚至殃及被告與已故兒子
between my client and his late son Yukio.
幸雄小弟弟之間的羈絆
This is unforgivable.
不可饒恕
Therefore,
基於以上證據 辯護人主張被告阿蘇重雄…
is innocent.
無罪
Those guys did whatever they pleased again.
那群傢伙似乎又擅自妄為了
If they lose, we'll have good reason to get rid of him.
不過要是他們打輸了 就能藉此處分了
What are you reading, Isawa?
你在看什麼，石和？
It's on the news that Mr. Kurokawa reversed the false charge.
是這次逆轉無罪的新聞
It's great advertisement for our office.
對我們事務所也會是很棒的宣傳呢
-Ouch. -Shut up and work.
-好痛 -吵死了，快工作
MAN IN ARSON CASE FOUND INNOCENT
（保險金縱火案男性獲判無罪）
DEFENSE'S EVIDENCE IS TRUSTWORTHY
（東京地方法院相信辯方鑑定）
FOUND INNOCENT
（獲判無罪）
I cannot thank all of you enough.
怎麼感謝各位都不夠
Thank you so much for your help.
真的受各位照顧了
Don't mention it.
不會
Where are you going to live?
找到地方住了嗎？
We decided to sell the land and move to the country.
我們決定把地賣了，去鄉下住
We couldn't let go of the house we lived in with our son,
我們之前一直捨不得離開 跟兒子一起生活過的家
but it's gone too.
但也都燒掉了
I see.
這樣啊
-Take care. -Thank you, everyone.
-請保重 -謝謝
Thank you.
謝謝
Goodbye.
那我們先走了
What's the matter?
怎麼了？看起來心情很差呢
If it had been on the news once,
只要被抓過一次，登上新聞
even if he's proved innocent,
就算冤罪洗清
people will still criticize him.
還是得遭受世人嚴苛的目光
That's also why they'll move to another place.
他們也是因此才得搬家的
I see.
這樣啊
It's my day off today.
那我今天先休假
Have a good rest.
好好休息吧
-See you later. -The loo…
-辛苦了 -洗手間…
TAKU KUROKAWA'S HOME
（黑川拓的家）
Come to think of it,
仔細想想
I've been left out of the loop at the end of this.
我到最後還是置身事外的
Nobody told me about the experiment beforehand too.
實驗的事也沒先跟我說
Because I asked them to.
是我要大家這樣做的
-We can't let you get in the way. -What do you mean?
-要是被妨礙就傷腦筋了 -什麼意思？
Mr. Beppu said various things to you, right?
所長應該跟你說了很多吧？
I wasn't going to get in the way of defending--
我又沒打算妨礙辯護…
I doubt it.
是嗎？那我差不多要回去了
My beloved son is waiting.
我心愛的兒子還在等我
-Ms. Kinosaki. -Yes?
-城崎小姐 -什麼事？
Is Mr. Kurokawa's father a legal professional?
黑川律師的父親是法曹相關人員嗎？
Why?
為什麼問這個？
The public prosecutor Ibusuki said he had met his father.
指宿檢察官說他見到黑川律師的父親
Did he?
是嗎？
Your son outwitted me again.
又被令郎擺了一道
I've read the judicial record.
我看了審判紀錄
It's because you cut corners.
是你們太偷懶了吧
I didn't, sir.
不，沒這回事
DEPUTY PROSECUTOR-GENERAL SUPREME PUBLIC PROSECUTORS OFFICE
（黑川真，最高檢察廳檢察官次長）
You insisted that the fire broke out from the son's bedroom,
執著於在小孩房放火的主張
that's why you were defeated.
就是敗因
If you had claimed that he set fire to the ground floor at the start,
只要一開始就主張是在一樓放火的
judging by the judge's impression,
從法官的自由心證看來 應該是能判有罪的
Thank you for your advice.
學到一課了
But sooner or later,
那傢伙總有一天 也會明白現實是怎麼回事的
Instead of proving someone's innocence,
比起洗刷冤罪
it's much more horrible to let someone go unpunished for his crime.
放過罪犯可怕得多了
Mr. Kurokawa's father is a public prosecutor?
檢察官？黑川律師的父親是檢察官？
Yes.
對，而且是最高檢察廳的檢察官次長
You're joking!
騙人
POST-WAR HISTORY OF FALSE VERDICTS
（《冤罪的戰後史》）
ENTERPRISE SENTAI SALAREADER 7,000 YEN
（企業戰隊超人，七千日圓）
OVERTIME RED
（加班紅戰士）
He really is the coolest!
這果然是最帥氣的
BUY NOW
（馬上購買）
THANK YOU FOR YOUR PURCHASE
（感謝購買）
I bought it!
買了
THIS DRAMA IS FICTITIOUS
（本劇純屬虛構）
A young man is arrested for robbing a convenience store.
因搶超商嫌疑而被逮捕的年輕人
I was going to queue.
我真的是想洗心革面的
Please help Takeo!
請幫幫岳雄
I'll investigate thoroughly and defend him.
我會徹底調查，奮戰到底
Can he prove Takeo's innocence?
是否能證明無罪？
Another shocking experiment is done.
衝擊性的實驗又將展開
There is no doubt he is innocent.
他絕對是清白的